<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sonic Writing</title>
    <description>A research blog for the AHRC funded Sonic Writing research project. This project explores how musical instrument design, musical notation techniques, and phonography is translated into current works in digital media.</description>
    <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.sonicwriting.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 13:43:56 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 13:43:56 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Notations Symposium @ IRCAM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the Sonic Writing research project, we are organising a symposium with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;IRCAM&lt;/a&gt;, Paris, on September 22nd, 2016. Further information on the symposium website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/ircam.html&quot;&gt;New Notations Symposium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus is on new notational practices in the context of recent developments in new instruments and media and key topics will address different aspects of musical instrumentalities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;notation and tradition - how does a notational language evolve?
&lt;li&gt;new instruments - how does the role of notation change with new technologies?
&lt;li&gt;the symbol and the material - do new ergonomic and timbral affordances require new symbolism?
&lt;li&gt;the evolving instrument - how do we compose for evolving technologies?
&lt;li&gt;notation in screen-based and computational media - what are the qualities of dynamic scores?
&lt;li&gt;graphic notation, live notation, animated notation - how does concept of &quot;liveness&quot; change?
&lt;li&gt;education and learning - how do we learn new notations for new digital instruments?
&lt;li&gt;audience understanding - how do we communicate what a notation system does?
&lt;li&gt;how does a notation system evolve, and how do we understand that evolution?
&lt;li&gt;what does a musical notation system mediate?
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/einar.png&quot; alt=&quot;From Desiring Machines&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;An extract of Einar Torfi Einarsson&#39;s work &lt;i&gt;Desiring Machines&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

The symposium blurb:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/ircam.html&quot;&gt;New Notations Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at IRCAM explores current notational practices in the writing for new instruments and media. The aim is to study the changes in notational strategies that are brought forward with new music technologies, where graphics, animation, and algorithmic techniques offer extended compositional possibilities. Musical notation and instruments evolve in parallel, and we find that in much contemporary work, the notation system becomes part of the instrument, or even an integral part of the musical piece itself. Processor-based media enable dynamic score systems that are applied to generate musical events in real-time or respond to instrumental performances in ways traditional media are not capable of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, with the increased analytical power gained with machine listening technologies, we find that auxillary notations of timbre, gesture, and affect become important aspects of the &quot;writing&quot; of a musical work. Contemporary composers study this potential of new notation, and this symposium looks into the design of new instruments from ergonomic and timbral perspectives and studies how musical notation develops in concert with these changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symposium topics include musical notation for new instruments, secondary notation, graphic or algorithmic notation, live and animated notation, usability, sustainability and legacy, tradition, issues of learning, audience communication, and more. The symposium consists of presentations, performances, and discussions. It is an open event, as long as space is available. For people interested in participating in the symposium, please fill in the registration form below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/cite&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters at the symposium are:&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;http://ultranoise.es/blog/&quot;&gt;Enrique Tomás&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.claudiamolitor.org&quot;&gt;Claudia Molitor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://frederic-bevilacqua.net&quot;&gt;Frédéric Bevilacqua&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uitti.org&quot;&gt;Frances-Marie Uitti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.orpheusinstituut.be/en/persons/jonathan-impett&quot;&gt;Jonathan Impett&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.socasites.qub.ac.uk/fschroeder/&quot;&gt;Franziska Schroeder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/profiles/240005&quot;&gt;Sally Jane Norman&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://pavlosantoniadis.wordpress.com/about&quot;&gt;Pavlos Antoniadis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://einartorfieinarsson.com&quot;&gt;Einar Torfi Einarsson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ryanrosssmith.com&quot;&gt;Ryan Ross Smith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 Dominique Fober&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://thormagnusson.github.io&quot;&gt;Thor Magnusson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/newnotations</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/newnotations</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Machine Creativity Roundtable at IASPM in Brighton</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We present a roundtable on Machine Creativity as part of the &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iaspm.org.uk/conference2016&quot;&gt;IASPM conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt; co-organised by the &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/music/&quot;&gt;Sussex Music Department&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt; and &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bimm.co.uk/brighton/&quot;&gt;BIMM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;. The idea is to set up a dialogue between researchers of machine creativity and popular music to further understanding between the respective fields. Members of the round table are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Elaine Chew&lt;/b&gt; - &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~eniale/&quot;&gt;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~eniale/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;
Chew is a musician (pianist) and mathematician (operations researcher) who designs mathematical and computational tools to model, analyse, and visualise music structures: structures constructed in the process of listening, performing, composing, and improvising.
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rebecca Fiebrink&lt;/b&gt; - &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doc.gold.ac.uk/~mas01rf/Rebecca_Fiebrink_Goldsmiths&quot;&gt;http://www.doc.gold.ac.uk/~mas01rf/Rebecca_Fiebrink_Goldsmiths&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fiebrink is an expert in machine learning and has created systems using neural networks that can quickly learn gestural and compositional styles of performers and composers. 

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Andrew McPherson&lt;/b&gt; - &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/people/view/20095/dr-andrew-mcpherson&quot;&gt;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/people/view/20095/dr-andrew-mcpherson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
How can computer algorithms add to and shape musical performance? Can instruments learn about the performers playing them? Can they contribute to the playing? Andrew will bring the NIME (New Instruments for Musical Expression) expertise to this round-table.

&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bob Sturm&lt;/b&gt; - &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~sturm/&quot;&gt;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~sturm/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Sturm’s research seeks to interrogate the “creative” and/or “intelligent” machine. Though a machine may appear creative and/or intelligent, what has it &lt;i&gt;actually&lt;/i&gt; learned to do? How can it be changed to do what we want it to do? Sturm will discuss various approaches to answering these questions, and how such &quot;learned machines&quot; can provide useful assistance and inspiration to the human creator.


&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thor Magnusson&lt;/b&gt; (chair) - &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/profiles/164902&quot;&gt;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/profiles/164902&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Thor Magnusson is a musician with a PhD in Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence, focusing on music software and the role of computers in musical creativity. &lt;/li&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/iaspm.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Tree of Porphyry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;IASPM 2016 conference poster&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The abstract for our roundtable is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;cite&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recent academic fields such as software studies, digital humanities, and the philosophy of technology have directed focus on big data, machine agency, and the role of algorithms in contemporary culture. We are slowly gaining a clearer understanding of the power, as well as pitfalls, of machinic involvement in daily human tasks. With machines that learn and communicate, we will see their powers used in domains that were seen as exclusively human, for example artistic creativity. However, the use of computational creativity in the domain of music is nothing new and one of the earliest computer music compositions - the Illiac Suite by Hiller and Isaacson - was composed applying Artificial Intelligence techniques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine creativity in the creative process can range from minor &quot;suggestions&quot; in filtering or mixing, or intelligent mapping between a controller and a sound generator, to a stronger involvement where the computer aids in writing in the style of a certain genre or a composer, even composing a whole musical piece without any human involvement. This raises both technical and philosophical questions about the nature of composition, performance, and creativity in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This proposed round-table addresses recent developments in machine learning, musical corpus analysis, and related computational creativity techniques. The session includes specialists in  machine creativity, who will present and discuss diverse aspects of how computers will be more involved in the creative process of future musical works. The panel will explore the potential of computational creativity in the musical domain, ranging from the use of AI in musical instruments, musical corpus analysis for deeper understanding and regeneration of music, and the use of AI for non-human music. The potential of semantic audio techniques will be questioned for the domains of film music, game sound and other fields where music has a specific context-aware functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The round-table will also discuss the role of the listener when musical works become open for interaction. How do new computational playback devices, in the form of mobile media, enable the listener to become part of the creative process of generating the music? What do these new technologies afford to composers, and how will they use AI as part of the new compositional context? &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will be discussing questions of computuational creativity and machine learning, and hoping to open up a dialogue with specialist in popular music studies. Some of the topics discussed include:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;li&gt; How is machine creativity being best applied in the field of music?
&lt;li&gt; Does machine creativity belong equally in performance and in composition/studio work?
&lt;li&gt; What is creativity? How does this concept operate in your field of research?
&lt;li&gt; Under which conditions can we declare a machine to be creative?
&lt;li&gt; What can a machine do that humans can&#39;t?
&lt;li&gt; Is there a difference in how computational algorithms would engage with established genres vs. experimental music?
&lt;li&gt; Wherein lies the art of music making? Will it perhaps always escape the machine?

&lt;p&gt;Our session will be at &lt;b&gt;1pm, on Saturday 10th of September&lt;/b&gt;. See full programme &lt;u&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iaspm.org.uk/iaspm/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/IASPM_Brighton_Schedule.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The header image of this post is Al-Jazari&#39;s Diagram of a hydropowered perpetual flute from &lt;i&gt;The Book of Knowledge of Ingenious Mechanical Devices&lt;/i&gt; from 1206. From &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AAl-jazari_water_device.jpg&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/machinecreativity</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/machinecreativity</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Musical Organics: A Symposium on Instrument Design</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 5th, a group of people will meet at STEIM in Amsterdam at a symposium called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/steim.html&quot;&gt;Musical Organics&lt;/a&gt;. The aim with the symposium is to question what instrument design means in the current age of new materials and media. Through a genealogical enquiry we hope to outline traces of design patterns that extend through histories of musical cultures, and observe how these are translated or transduced by the migration into the seemingly infinite space offered by digital media. The symposium features presentations by a violin luthier, an artist instrument maker, engineers, designers, live coders, composers, and performers. Common to all these people is an interdisciplinary approach that crosses professional boundaries, through a practice that reaches beyond the granularity of our current language. The new materialities require new languages.

&lt;p&gt;Traditional organology (the science of musical instruments) is a study of the history and classification of musical instruments. Diverse classification schemes have been proposed, extending back to the ancient Greeks, who proposed a three-fold system of wind, string and percussion instruments. These organologies are hierarchical, with diverse levels, classes and branches. Some of these systems are incredibly nuanced, for example Montagu and Burton&#39;s scheme that has the following tree structure: kingdom (all noise makers), sub-kingdom (airophones, chordophones, membranophones, and idiophones), super-phylum (e.g., struck idiophones), phylum, class, order, sub-order, family, sub-family, genus, species, sub-species, and variety. There is a clear inheritance here to the classificatory metaphysics we find in Aristotle&#39;s &lt;i&gt;categories&lt;/i&gt;, which later became represented by classical tree structure hierarchies, known in medieval times as &lt;i&gt;Arbor Porphyriana&lt;/i&gt; (or the Tree of Porphyry).

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/arbor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Tree of Porphyry&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;The classificatory philosophical tree of &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AArborLulle.jpg&quot;&gt;Lully&lt;/a&gt;, based on Porphyry&#39;s &lt;i&gt;Isagoge&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common and well known organology is the system proposed by Sachs and Hornbostel in 1914. This system expands the early Greek one, and defines &lt;i&gt;idiophones&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;membranophones&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;chordophones&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;aerophones&lt;/i&gt;. This organology allows for a clear typological tracing down to the unique features of the individual instrument, where, for example, the numerical denominator of 111.242.222 would refer to sets of hanging bells with internal strikers (1 = idiophone; 11 = struck idiophone; 111 = idiophones struck directly; 111.2 = percussion idiophones; 111.24 = percussion vessels; 111.242 = bells; 111.242.2 = sets of bells; 111.242.22 = sets of suspended bells; 111.242.222 = sets of clapper bells). This classification system, with such a nuanced cataloguing of instruments, is clearly useful for museums, historians, anthropologists, and some musicologists (I say &#39;some&#39;, as there has arguably been a gap between Western organology and musicology, a symptom of the rift we find in phiosophy between &lt;i&gt;episteme&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;techne&lt;/i&gt;, as introduced by Plato). 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/kirscher.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kirscher&#39;s Aeolian Harp&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Kirscher&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Fotothek_df_tg_0008349_Akustik_%5E_Schall_%5E_Harfe_%5E_Aeolsharfe_%5E_Windharfe_%5E_Musikinstrument_%5E_Saiteninst.jpg&quot;&gt;Aeolian Harp&lt;/a&gt; from 1684 is an example of an instrument that breaks traditional organologies, as acknowledged by Sachs and Hornbostel in the introduction to their original work&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1940, Sachs added the fifth category to the scheme, the &lt;i&gt;electrophone&lt;/i&gt;. This was in turn divided into three sub-categories: electric-action, electro-mechanical, and radioelectric. Other organologists have continued applying the electrophone category and developing it. But here is the problem: with digital media, we get a material substance of such a plastic and dynamic nature - due to the computer being a meta-machine - that the concept of electrophone is clearly becoming inadequate. The introduction of a category like &lt;i&gt;digitophone&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;digiphone&lt;/i&gt; would not solve many problems. The fact is that digital musical systems, as implemented in software for computers, integrated in hardware, or in the form of mobile apps, are so open and diverse, deriving their design patterns from an extremely heterogeneous sources of musical technics, that fitting them into genealogical trees of tradititional organologies is an unworkable task. This impossibility is amplified further by the fact that the digiphones (if we are to temporarily entertain that organological category) equally originate from the worlds of digital design, human-computer interaction, and computer games. Such an organology would therefore have to be a project of interdisciplinary and intermedia nature.

&lt;p&gt;For this reason, and instead of improved organologies, we organise a symposium on musical organics: an attempt at exploring and framing the ecosystems of musical technics as a reticulated web - one that hybridises older organologies, continually borrowing, referencing, appropriating, and representing the techniques incorporated in human movement. This would be a heterarchical organology - a contradiction in terms - and thus the symposium name of &lt;i&gt;Musical Organics&lt;/i&gt;, referencing soil, plants, flowers, or perhaps the ultra-famous &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gnteiRO-XfU&quot;&gt;rhizome&lt;/a&gt;. This move mirrors Umberto Eco&#39;s criticism of the dictionary in favour of the more organisationally flexible scheme of the encyclopedia.



&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/musicalorganics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/musicalorganics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Critical Music Technology</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Teaching music in Higher Education, in particular musical practices that make use of computers as tools for performance and composing, one cannot help but notice how colleagues in diverse universities across the country complain about the received definition of &quot;music technology.&quot; This definition frames music technology as the production of music made with a specific set of equipment; a musical practice that excludes wider activities, such as note-based composition, live performance, audiovisual composition, or the non-linear music found in apps and games. Colleagues frequently report on how the first meeting with new students always involves an encouragement for a more open minded approach to musical composition and performance with new digital technologies. The question often asked is where this narrow concept of music technology originates from?

&lt;p&gt;We could attempt to find an answer by examining how the subject called &quot;music technology&quot; is taught in secondary education. Here, we become acutely aware of a rather narrow focus and it interesting to discover that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/organisations/ofqual&quot;&gt;Ofqual&lt;/a&gt; has recently forged a stronger separation in the subject criteria for Music and Music Technology. This is done by means of a definintion of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://qualifications.pearson.com/en/qualifications/edexcel-a-levels/music-technology-2008.news.html?article=%2Fcontent%2Fdemo%2Fen%2Fnews-policy%2Fqualifications%2Fa-levels%2Fmusic-technology%2Fas-a-level-music-technology-subject-criteria-consultation-now-open&quot;&gt; criteria for Music Technology&lt;/a&gt; into four separate themes that have now been confirmed in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/504470/First_Teach_2017_Part_1_-_decisions_document_including_sociology.pdf&quot;&gt; Ofcom document&lt;/a&gt; to be implemented in 2017. Now the four themes have become the following Assessment Objectives:

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate use of music technology to capture, edit and produce recordings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate use of music technology to create, edit and structure sounds to develop a technology based composition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate and apply knowledge and understanding of music technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use analytical and appraising skills to make evaluative and critical judgements about the use of music technology&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a document published in January 2016, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/504026/GCSE_A_level_reform_subject_content_government_response.pdf&quot;&gt;Reformed GCSE, AS and A level subjects&lt;/a&gt;, we read that government policy is to increase &quot;emphasis on theoretical, technical and scientific understanding&quot; (p.38) with more &quot;mathematics and technical content.&quot; The idea is to create a stronger identity and separation between Music and Music Technology as two distinct disciplines. This is achieved by removing &quot;content which overlapped with AS and A level music as this created a rigorous subject with its own distinct knowledge and understanding.&quot; And one wonders whether performance and composition are amongst the excluded content. 

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it is evident that musical performance, written notated music, the design of new instruments, generative music, music for the moving image, live coding, sound installations, or sound design and music for computer games are greatly under-represented. Not to mention musicological approaches. This is an education that focuses on a specific set of equipment, where the producer is a consumer of technologies that are beyond the user to adopt or change (unlike what we saw in the studio activities of George Martin or Lee Scratch Perry). Indeed, the Ofqual documents suggest that the curriculum is designed for a 20th century music industry that has now been superseded with a much more diverse, energetic, and interdisciplinary field. 

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say that all the work we do in higher education aiming to correct the gender imbalance in music technology degrees is not helped by this type of language. My experience is that a holistic language that includes references to creativity, performance, art, audience, culture, collaboration, and communication will attract a much wider demography than a language centred on equipment and scientific terminology. (An excellent study on diversity in music technology is Georgina Born and Kyle Devine&#39;s article &quot;Music Technology, Gender, and Class: Digitization, Educational and Social Change in Britain&quot; in the &lt;i&gt;20th Century Music&lt;/i&gt; Journal).

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/mixer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a mixer&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;A familiar &quot;music technology&quot; iconography.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above illustrates the need for some critical re-thinking of what music technologies actually are. The common connotation of “music technology,” involves plastic- or metal-surfaced equipment offering interaction through rotating knobs, sliders, or buttons, which are mapped to functionality represented on a screen of some sort. It is the space-ship interface for powerful control over sound. However, a quick etymology of the word “technology” clearly demonstrates that we are not discussing plastic gadgets here, but rather an embodied knowledge, skill or craft. The roots of the Greek word &lt;i&gt;technê&lt;/i&gt; is “wood,” but at the time of the early philosophers, it had begun to denote the craft of producing something out of something else. For Aristotle, &lt;i&gt;technê&lt;/i&gt; is an activity where the &lt;i&gt;“origin is in the maker and not in the thing made.”&lt;/i&gt; In his work Rhetorics, Aristotle uses the word “technology” to signify the “craft of the word” (techne and logos) as used in grammar or rhetorics, which is an inverse meaning to the later use signifying the knowledge (logy) of craft (techne). The word is not used much until the 17th century, which is when it enters the English language. At no point did the word signify objects, but rather the skill of doing things, as evidenced Marx’s Das Kapital: &lt;i&gt;“Technology discloses man’s mode of dealing with Nature, the process of production by which he sustains his life, and thereby also lays bare the mode of formation of his social relations, and of the mental conceptions that flow from them.”&lt;/i&gt; Earlier in the same paragraph we read: &lt;i&gt;“Darwin has interested us in the history of Nature’s Technology,”&lt;/i&gt; and it is clear that he means the ways nature goes about its business. Bernard Stiegler defines technology as &lt;i&gt;“the discourse describing and explaining the evolution of specialised procedures and techniques, arts and trades”&lt;/i&gt; and encourages us to use the word in the manner we apply the words “psychology” or “sociology”.

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; music technology: we don’t buy it, own it, or use it. Thinking, designing, discussing, performing and composing are all acts of music technological nature. Musical instruments, musical notation, recording equipment and media players are the tools of music technology and represent the musico-theoretical framework of each culture. In this context we observe that musical instruments are indeed amongst the earliest human technologies. Possibly preceding fire and weaponry, we could speculate how early humans used rocks or sticks to hit other materials in order to define territories, communicate, or synchronise movements. Some of the oldest known musical instruments are flutes found in Germany (the &lt;i&gt;Hohle Fels&lt;/i&gt; flute) and Slovenia (the &lt;i&gt;Divje Babe&lt;/i&gt; flute), thought to be between 35,000 and 42,000 years old. Preceding those flutes would be generations of forgotten instruments in the form of rocks and sticks which might not even “look like” musical instruments at all, but they represent the music technologies of the time. 

&lt;p&gt;To do music technology thus involves studying the environment in which new music is produced, critically reflecting upon how musical practices are determined by the tools at hand, which, in turn, are also conditioned by what we do with them. But more importantly, it means to perform, improvise, collaborate and redefine equipment for new contexts and explore their musical limits. The history of the saxophone is a good example of how undefined a musical instrument can be at first, slowly gaining a function amongst different musical cultures such as military bands and jazz. In this context it is interesting to behold Attali’s statement that in &lt;i&gt;“music, the instrument often predates the expression it authorizes, which explains why a new invention has the nature of noise; a ‘realized theory’ (Lyotard), it contributes, through the possibilities it offers, to the birth of a new music, a renewed syntax.”&lt;/i&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;A critical questioning of music technology implies the study of how our music technologies are conditioned by the complex interrelationship of aesthetics, science, culture, and equipment. We should embrace the fact that music techno-logy is the knowledge of the craft of music, and that craft has traditionally, for at least 40 millennia, been about performing music, about people gathering together to play, share, contribute, live the moment, and enjoy the unexpected. The design and use of a bone flute, a lute, a musical score, or a digital audio workstation are all good examples of music technology. Entering the 21st century, we bring all that baggage with us, but let&#39;s unpack it in the context of new musical practices - of new musical technologies.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/musictechnology</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/musictechnology</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ICLI 2016: The 3rd International Conference on Live Interfaces</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Members of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.miptl.org&quot;&gt;Music Informatics and Performance Technologies Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Sussex are organising the 3rd &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org&quot;&gt;International Conference on Live Interfaces&lt;/a&gt;. This biennial conference began at the University of Leeds in 2012, and was then held in Lisbon in 2014. We are very excited to be hosting the third instance of this fantastic conference in Brighton this summer, at the University of Sussex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference website can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org&quot;&gt;http://www.liveinterfaces.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ICLI conference is an interdisciplinary summit that focusses on performance technologies in all artistic human activities. There are more bespoke conferences on new interfaces in music (such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nime.org&quot;&gt;NIME&lt;/a&gt;), but ICLI is unique in that it aims to understand how the different art forms engage with concepts of interface, embodiment, live performance, improvisation and technical skill. We can learn much from each other as practitioners in the diverse art forms, and there was a bespoke need in creating this platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to stress the interdisciplinary nature of the conference, we have invited keynote speakers from three distinct fields of practice: &lt;a href=&quot;http://tinything.com/&quot;&gt;Kristina Andersen&lt;/a&gt; (music), &lt;a href=&quot;http://stuartnolan.com&quot;&gt;Stuart Nolan&lt;/a&gt; (magic), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://watermillcenter.org/residency/roman-paska&quot;&gt;Roman Paska&lt;/a&gt; (puppetry). We are hoping the diversity of topics listed in the call will encourage people from as diverse performing art forms as dance, puppetry, music, performance art, magic, computer games, comedy, visual arts, video art, and many more. The boundaries are fuzzy, of course, as some might argue that live interfaces are also used in expressive ways in martial arts, religious ceremonies, or gastronomy, to name but a few examples, but we will await decisions from our excellent reviewer team to define what kind of conference this will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference will include the potential for a strong public involvement, where people will be able to attend special events during the conference or getting a day ticket for selected days. The conference will be one of the first public engagement activities of the newly refurbished &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/acca/&quot;&gt;ACCA&lt;/a&gt; (Attenborough Centre for Creative Arts), and the event benefits from the strong support by its creative director, Paula McDermott.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/acca.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;inspecting ACCA&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Some members of the ICLI team inspecting the conference location at ACCA (Attenborough Centre for Creative Arts).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are very excited about two resonating instruments workshops that will take place before the conference starts. During these workshops, composers and performers will be teamed up to study, compose and perform on two quite unique instruments: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.halldorulfarsson.info/halldorophones/about-halldorophones&quot;&gt;halldorophone&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~andrewm/mrp.html&quot;&gt;Magnetic Resonator Piano&lt;/a&gt;. These sessions will be lead by the instrument designers Halldor Ulfarsson and Andrew McPherson, together with skilled performers &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecila.org&quot;&gt;Alice Eldridge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sarahnicolls.com&quot;&gt;Sarah Nicolls&lt;/a&gt;. There will be other workshops during the conference, but those will be proposed through the submissions and go through our peer review process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deadline for submissions has been extended to February 21st, so please consider submitting a performance proposal, a paper, a workshop, an installation or participate in the doctoral colloquium. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2016 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/icli</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/icli</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello World: Launching the Sonic Writing Project</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This website will document research activities relating to a two-year &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahrc.ac.uk&quot;&gt;AHRC&lt;/a&gt; funded fellowship starting on February 1st, 2016. The Sonic Writing research project aims to investigate the complex relationship between musical instrument design, musical notation, and phonography, in order to get a better understanding of how digital media transform these established musical practices. The transduction process that takes place when digital media become the prevalent platform for musical production, dissemination, and consumption is exciting, yet deeply problematic, as with the abundance of new techniques and social connectivity brought by the digital media, we also leave behind knowledge and practices that are not translated into the digital. Entailed in the digital is an abstraction and representation of reality, a process that is bound to exclude features, add new ones, and marginalise others. The question of how musical traditions can be preserved in digital media is a real and pressing one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary output of the project is a book, &lt;i&gt;Sonic Writing: Technologies of Musical Expression Notation and Encoding&lt;/i&gt;, which will be published by Bloomsbury&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/academic/academic-subjects/music-and-sound-studies/&quot;&gt;Music &amp;amp; Sound Studies&lt;/a&gt; series. The research is conducted with five project partners: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;IRCAM&lt;/a&gt; in Paris, &lt;a href=&quot;http://steim.org&quot;&gt;STEIM&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cnmat.berkeley.edu&quot;&gt;CNMAT&lt;/a&gt; in Berkeley, &lt;a href=&quot;http://music.columbia.edu/cmc/&quot;&gt;CMC&lt;/a&gt; in New York, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://c4dm.eecs.qmul.ac.uk&quot;&gt;C4DM&lt;/a&gt; (Queen Mary) in London. These will host residencies where the research team will organise workshops and symposia on key research themes: instrument design, musical notation, phonography (including machine listening), and music in digital media. Workshops and symposia will be advertised here and on other media outlets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is in many ways building on the experiences and knowledge gained from running the highly active &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.livecodenetwork.org&quot;&gt;Live Code Research Network&lt;/a&gt; together with &lt;a href=&quot;http://yaxu.org&quot;&gt;Alex McLean&lt;/a&gt;. The past two years have been amazing and I thank you Alex for the wonderful collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will result in various outputs: software, papers, articles, symposia, an international conference (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org/&quot;&gt;ICLI&lt;/a&gt;), and a book. For news and updates on events, please follow &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/thormagnusson&quot;&gt;@thormagnusson&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launching an extensive research project is exciting: feelings of anticipation, curiosity, and adventure coalseque with the agitation involving entering territories of the unknown. With me on the journey are two other research team members, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samduffysax.webspace.virginmedia.com/indexSamDuffySinger/Home.html&quot;&gt;Sam Duffy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://alexanderpeverett.com&quot;&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/a&gt;, who are perfectly placed to make this journey both academically fruitful and fun. Here is to the next two years!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/helloworld</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/helloworld</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
