<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sonic Writing</title>
    <description>A research blog for the AHRC funded Sonic Writing research project. This project explores how musical instrument design, musical notation techniques, and phonography is translated into current works in digital media.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 12:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2020 12:35:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Previews, Interviews and Reviews of Sonic Writing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My book, Sonic Writing, was published a year ago. I’ve been surprisingly pleased with its reception and to learn that people whose work I’m continually inspired by are praising the book, using it in their teaching and recommending it as required reading for lab members. The book would not exist without these people and I’m glad that ideas are feeding back the other direction too. Here below I present a mix of interviews, presentations and reviews of the book I’ve participated in or been made aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first review of the book was by Gregory Taylor on the Cycling74 page: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cycling74.com/articles/book-review-sonic-writing&quot;&gt;Book Review: Sonic Writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prolific Darwin Grosse interviewed me for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://artmusictech.libsyn.com/podcast-289-thor-magnusson&quot;&gt;Art+Music+Technology Podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: none&quot; src=&quot;//html5-player.libsyn.com/embed/episode/id/10900775/height/90/theme/custom/thumbnail/yes/direction/forward/render-playlist/no/custom-color/000000/&quot; height=&quot;90&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; oallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; msallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-scripts&quot; allow=&quot;geolocation&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discussed the book with Eamonn Bell from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://newbooksnetwork.com/thor-magnusson-sonic-writing-technologies-of-material-symbolic-and-signal-inscriptions-bloomsbury-academic-2019/&quot;&gt;New Books Network&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;220&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://playlist.megaphone.fm/?e=LIT2439898405&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; sandbox=&quot;allow-same-origin allow-scripts&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little teaser presentation of the book at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rewirefestival.nl/event/instrumental-shifts-symposium&quot;&gt;Instrumental Shifts Symposium&lt;/a&gt; during the Dutch ReWire festival:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://player.vimeo.com/video/344784065&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; fullscreen&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neural Magazine had a review of the book in their &lt;a href=&quot;http://neural.it/2020/02/thor-magnusson-sonic-writing-technologies-of-material-symbolic-and-signal-inscriptions/&quot;&gt;February Issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/Neural.png&quot; alt=&quot;Neural Sonic Writing Review&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antonio Poscic wrote a review for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://reader.exacteditions.com/issues/82170/spread/1&quot;&gt;February 2019&lt;/a&gt; issue of the Wire Magazine:
&lt;a href=&quot;/media/Wire.png&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/media/Wire.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wire Sonic Writing Review&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Diana Chester wrote a review for the Issue 7 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.interferencejournal.org&quot;&gt;Interference Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;/js/pdfobject.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pdf1&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
.pdfobject-container { height: 40rem; border: 1rem solid rgba(0,0,0,.1); }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script&gt;PDFObject.embed(&quot;/media/Interference.pdf&quot;, &quot;#pdf1&quot;);&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.sonicwriting.org/media/Interference.pdf&amp;embedded=true&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:400px;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr John Dack wrote a review in The Journal of &lt;a href=&quot;https://muse.jhu.edu/issue/42132&quot;&gt;Technology and Culture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pdf2&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;PDFObject.embed(&quot;/media/TechnologyCulture.pdf&quot;, &quot;#pdf2&quot;);&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.sonicwriting.org/media/TechnologyCulture.pdf&amp;embedded=true&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:400px;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Davic C. Jackson presents a review in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/20551940.2020.1742413?&quot;&gt;The Sound Studies Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;pdf3&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;PDFObject.embed(&quot;/media/SoundStudies.pdf&quot;, &quot;#pdf3&quot;);&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;!--
&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.sonicwriting.org/media/SoundStudies.pdf&amp;embedded=true&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:400px;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;(c) 2016-2020 &amp;THORN;&amp;oacute;rhallur Magn&amp;uacute;sson, Thorhallur Magnusson, Thor Magnusson&lt;/font&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 20:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/reviews</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/reviews</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonic Writing - A book on new musics and technologies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sonic Writing is now out with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomsbury.com/9781501313868&quot;&gt;Bloomsbury Academic&lt;/a&gt;. This monograph is the final outcome of an &lt;a href=&quot;https://ahrc.ukri.org&quot;&gt;AHRC&lt;/a&gt; funded &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org&quot;&gt;research project&lt;/a&gt; that ran between 2016 and 2018. The book is divided into four key parts: &lt;b&gt;instruments&lt;/b&gt; (material inscriptions), &lt;b&gt;notation&lt;/b&gt; (symbolic inscriptions), &lt;b&gt;recording&lt;/b&gt; (signal inscriptions), and &lt;b&gt;new music technologies&lt;/b&gt;, or how our analogue and electronic traditions are translated and applied in the design of digital instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic Writing explores the unique relationship we have with our musical instruments - our technologies for making sound. I’ve come to realise there are very few things that humans have such an intimate and caring relationship with as musical instruments. These technologies have evolved over millennia and through instruments, systems design, theory, notation, phonography, computational creativity and now machine learning and AI, music has always been at the cusp of our technological development and understanding. Musical instruments are unique technologies: they are at the same time an instrument to look into our inner self and to speculate about new cultural forms. Sonic Writing tries to understand the role of technologies of music making in wider cultural practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this research programme I ran symposia and workshops at &lt;a href=&quot;http://steim.org&quot;&gt;STEIM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;IRCAM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://c4dm.eecs.qmul.ac.uk&quot;&gt;C4DM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmc.music.columbia.edu&quot;&gt;CMC&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cnmat.berkeley.edu&quot;&gt;CNMAT&lt;/a&gt;; and a writer’s residency at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fondation-janmichalski.com/en/fondation/&quot;&gt;Jan Michalski Fondation&lt;/a&gt; - all events, places and people that greatly inspired the way the book developed. Through discussions with colleagues working on cutting-edge research, a more refined understanding of the integrated relationship between contemporary music and its technology began to emerge, and I hope I was able to represent that vision in my book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of my travels, I had the opportunity to interview people whose practice shapes the changes I describe in my book. I am extremely grateful to these people: Kristina Andersen, Margaret Birley, Ken Butler, Ed Campion, Suzanne Ciani, Nick Collins, Pierre Couprie, Pete Furniss, Brad Garton, Rama Gottfried, Derek Holzer, Hans Jóhannsson, Shinji Kanki, Roger Linn, James McCartney, Alex McLean, Andrew McPherson, Claudia Molitor, Sarah Nicolls, Godfried-Willem Raes, Christopher Redgate, Ryan Ross Smith, Laetitia Sonami, Laurie Spiegel, Dan Stowell, Bob Sturm, Enrique Tomás, Ge Wang, Anna Xambó, and Pamela Z. I have the feeling that more material will emerge as a result of these interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read a sample chapter by clicking on this image:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://bloomsburycp3.codemantra.com/viewer/5ea80fb552faff00016b0300&quot;&gt;
&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;W3Schools&quot; src=&quot;/img/boneband.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I enjoy writing, initially I wasn’t sure if a printed book would be the right format for this type of research. Perhaps an online publication where I could link to sounds, videos, pictures, and artist websites would be more practical? Where people could comment, add notes, and further contribute to the development of the research. However, in the end the printed book format was simply too attractive, or, as it says in the preface: “there is a quality of the printed format that I value: to constrain, focus, write, rewrite, rehearse, rethink, review, edit and re-edit in an iterative process that involves colleagues, editors, proofreaders, and myself operating in a tradition that extends back to antiquity and is endowed with its own rules, protocols, and formats.” And I don’t regret this decision - hard work, but worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cover artwork is a piece by Ryan Ross Smith, &lt;i&gt;Study 56&lt;/i&gt;. It is an animated notation piece where performers play from a computer generated dynamic score. I think this beautiful still suits the cover of the book, as the book represents a definite moment in time, a snapshot of the dynamic everchaning field of music, just like a screengrab of an animated score. The piece is a generative application, and one rendering of it can be seen here below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Wj8Rej53b9M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a launch party in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt; Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt; on March 14th - all welcome! In addition to drinks and snacks, we will hear music by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.feedbackcell.info&quot;&gt;Feedback Cell&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://alexanderpeverett.com&quot;&gt;Alex Peverett&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrew-duff.co.uk&quot;&gt;Andrew Duff&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evelynficarra.net/about/&quot;&gt;Evelyn Ficarra&lt;/a&gt;. All of these people have inspired the book, so I’m thrilled to have them performing during the launch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bloomsbury gave me a discount code that can be used if you purchase the book on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomsbury.com/9781501313868&quot;&gt;Bloomsbury website&lt;/a&gt; : “GLR MP6”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ahrc.ukri.org&quot;&gt;
&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;AHRC logo&quot; src=&quot;/img/ahrc.png&quot; width=&quot;220&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl&quot;&gt;
&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;SHL logo&quot; src=&quot;/img/shl.jpg&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/music&quot;&gt;
&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;Sussex logo&quot; src=&quot;/img/USlogo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; height=&quot;80&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;font color=&quot;#FFFFFF&quot;&gt;(c) 2016-2019 &amp;THORN;&amp;oacute;rhallur Magn&amp;uacute;sson, Thorhallur Magnusson, Thor Magnusson&lt;/font&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/sonicwriting</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/sonicwriting</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ergodynamics - on the haecceity of musical instruments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;There is something magical about musical instruments: we pick them up, tune into their mode of communication, and we transcend into a different &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Form_of_life_(philosophy)&quot;&gt;form of life&lt;/a&gt;. The instrument is what constitutes this possibility of a different thought and voice: it is a torch into our inner being. Trying a new instrument for the first time is a peculiar encounter: we rotate the instrument, observe it from all angles, pluck it, blow it, stroke it, shake it, hit it and generally explore what it offers us in terms of interesting expression. This process can take hours, weeks, years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having become familiar with the instrument, we roam its expressive scope, as if exploring a landscape that is covered by a fog, but there within we come upon beautiful local areas that entice and attract. This is about finding the constraints of the instrument, a path to mastery that requires time and effort: a process of discovery, of research. Not only are instrumental types different, and we operate with complex classifications of musical instruments (see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/blog/musicalorganics&quot;&gt;Musical Organics&lt;/a&gt; blogpost), but every individual instrument is unique! No two instruments are the same when the come from the luthier or the factory, and they further develop in your hands, gaining a unique form that separates it from other instances of the same type from the same maker. This is the instrument’s &lt;i&gt;haecceity&lt;/i&gt;, its unique qualities, place and behaviour in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/21oboe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Christopher Redgate's 21st Century Oboe&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Christopher Redgate's 21st Century Oboe&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When discussing these things with people, I have been seeking a vocabulary that covers how we talk about our instruments. A terminology that is similar to how ludologists might deliberate about the “gameplay” of a computer game, as its general feel, play, navigation, aesthetics, game mechanics, pace, possibilities, etc. What analogous word to “gameplay” can we use in organology? Design, playability, character, tone, affordances, constraints, remediation, ergonomics, workflow and expressiveness are not ideal words as they are specific, limited and often technical. I became interested in developing a terminology based on the function of the instruments, their working nature and character. &lt;i&gt;Ergos&lt;/i&gt; is the Greek term for work (and we can see the direct etymological relation to “work”, “werk”, “verk” in other European languages). It also relates to the term “organ” which is Greek for instrument, but one that is equially a bodily organ (like the heart), a tool (like the hammer) or a musical instrument (like the harp). So instruments work, they operate and are operated; they work and are worked. Instruments are functional tools, they perform functions and are pregnant with undiscovered potential. This is the dynamic range of the instrument, or its &lt;i&gt;dynamis&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the search for terminology I therefore began exploring whether the term &lt;i&gt;ergodynamics&lt;/i&gt; would work as a term describing the potential of an instrument, its range, scope, expressivity. Like the ludologist would say “this game has a good gameplay” we musicians might now describe an instrument as having interesting ergodynamics. This is referring to the mystery, depth, hidden features, discoverability embedded in the object. And what amazing objects musical instruments are! Humans rarely engage with other objects this way, although I must admit that I have talked with skateboarders about skateboards, chefs about knifes, dentists about drills, archers about bows and whilst those are also quite obsessed with their objects, the musical instrument constitutes something more: it’s a way to express inner states withouth the crude and clumsy formulations of language. Human thinking without having to put the world into the rigid categories of symbols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related terms became &lt;i&gt;ergomimesis&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;ergography&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;ergophor&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming up with a group of descriptive terms for musical instruments as a contribution to organological vocabolary is a strange thing to do, so in my self-doubt I discussed with colleagues, with Greeks, with instrumentalists, with linguists and with luthiers. I presented a paper at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org/2018/pdf/ICLI2018-Magnusson.pdf&quot;&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt;, wrote an article in a &lt;a href=&quot; https://doi.org/10.1017/S0040298218000633&quot;&gt;journal&lt;/a&gt;, and gave a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://sparc.london/touch-symposium/&quot;&gt;talks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ufg.at/Archivdetail.2267+M58916929d4d.0.html&quot;&gt;workshops&lt;/a&gt; about this, all with the aim to see if people could help me realising how ridiculous this excercise was. Well, they didn’t. So I used the concepts in my forthcoming book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bloomsbury.com/uk/sonic-writing-9781501313868/&quot;&gt;Sonic Writing&lt;/a&gt;. More on that book very soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org/2018/pdf/ICLI2018-Magnusson.pdf&quot;&gt;Ergomimesis: Towards a Language Describing Instrumental Transductions&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
In the proceedings of the 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.liveinterfaces.org/2018&quot;&gt;International Conference on Live Interfaces&lt;/a&gt; in Porto.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0040298218000633&quot;&gt;Ergodynamics and a Semiotics of Instrumental Composition&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Published in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/tempo&quot;&gt;Tempo Journal&lt;/a&gt; in January 2019.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bloomsbury.com/uk/sonic-writing-9781501313868/&quot;&gt;Sonic Writing: Technologies of Material, Symbolic and Signal Inscriptions&lt;/a&gt; published by Bloomsbury Academic in 2019. [Here is a 35% discount code: “GLR MP6”]&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Feb 2019 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/ergodynamics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/ergodynamics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Presenting Musical Organics - Ideation &amp; Feedback</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;i&gt;Sonic Writing&lt;/i&gt; research project, I’ve been thinking about the classification of digital instruments, since the materiality of these technologies poses considerable problems for traditional organologies. Philosophical ideas mature slowly, and in my experience they develop best in conversation, presentation, or practical development, where technical problems and alternative views emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideation is the process in which ideas are born and take form, for example through language, sound, paint, or machines. The intuition I had for the concept of “musical organics” was based on over two decades of working with all kinds of musical instruments, building and playing them, but always sensing the different nature of our new digital instruments; a certain unease always accompanies the first encounter with a digital instrument. It is not easy to express this feeling, and in conversation with people one senses this unease in what is being said often implicitly, typically tacitly. Now, I love what the computer has enabled us to do in music — what a tool! — but there is something unique in the relationship performers have with their acoustic instruments, with the wood, strings, metal, bones, horsehair and other materials that are so full of character, all so different, to the degree that each and every instrument is unique (a violin bow you pick up in a shop might be very different from an “identical” violin bow lying next to it). And that’s when they are new and have only been manipulated by the hands the luthier - imgagine their difference when they have been “played in” by the instrumentalist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is no news to anyone who has a background in traditional instruments but shifted over to the computer when it became powerful enough for musical expression. (Enrike Hurtado and myself did a survey on that question in 2006, with the results published at NIME 2007, with a little upgrade for &lt;a href=&quot;http://econtact.ca/10_4/magnusson_hurtado_survey.html&quot;&gt; eContact&lt;/a&gt;, and now more recently for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.springer.com/gb/book/9783319472133&quot;&gt;NIME Reader&lt;/a&gt;). I’ve been interested in this question for a long time, or since I parked my electric guitar for the new languages of the computer. My perceived sense of alienation from the musical object was immediate: the phenomenological complexity in digital instruments becomes so prominent when compared with acoustic instruments, but this is also what makes the digital domain so powerful (a bit like how AI helps us to do work in cognitive science).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development of the concept of musical organics involved various engagements: a symposium organised with &lt;a href=&quot;http://steim.org&quot;&gt;STEIM&lt;/a&gt;, a paper presentation at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nime2017.org&quot;&gt;NIME&lt;/a&gt;, a presentation at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dpassh.org/2017/03/07/papers-and-presentations-announced/&quot;&gt;DPASSH conference&lt;/a&gt;, an article for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/nnmr20/46/3?nav=tocList&quot;&gt;Journal of New Music Research&lt;/a&gt;, and a provocation at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sparc.london/touch-symposium&quot;&gt;Touching Sound symposium&lt;/a&gt; held at City University. Through these events, following discussions with colleagues, the concept of musical organics is emerging and taking a fuller shape. This will be described here below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/musicalorganics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Musurgia Universalis&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;From Kirscher's Musurgia Universalis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/steim.html&quot;&gt;Musical Organics Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at STEIM in Amsterdam, held in May 2016, involved instrument makers (designers, luthiers, programmers, engineers), composers, and performers. The idea was to summon a diverse group together for presentations, performances and workshops. The first day ran with presentations and performances, followed, on the second day, by discussions and workshops. All of this extended into the early hours in the wonderful restaurants and bars of Amsterdam. The participants in this symposium all came with their own research agenda, and judging from feedback it was a useful experience for them. I myself had a few theoretical irons in the fire and I used the two days to observe, probe, and interpret the proceedings. I presented an early draft of the musical organics idea, and got very useful feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time then came for actual research. Having been interested in classification since spending a good part of 1997 reading the whole of Nietzsche’s writings, I subscribe to his pessimism in natural language and our conceptual systems. Classification is about understanding, about ordering, about putting things into place, and that is why, in the 17th century, when modern science is born, we find this obsession with measuring, analysing, and classifying. If we are to understand digital instruments, a natural approach is the attempt to analyse their properties, put them into groups, order them, classify (this is of course useful if we are organising a book about instruments, creating an online shop, or arranging the instruments in a museum). However, provided the diverse origins and disparate fluid nature of digital instruments, we are bound to ask ourselves how this might be achieved? Greek theory, medieval classification, 16th and 17th century approaches, all culminating in late 19th century and early 20th century tree-like classifications; it is clear that this is a road to despair. Instead, a fuller idea emerged, from the vague intuition that drove this research from the start, namely a non-hierarchical, interconnected, perspectival system of dynamic ordering. If we can’t put place these phenomena onto trees, let’s reticulate them in a web that can be rearranged according to the perspective the researcher is interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These thoughts have now been published in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/nnmr20/46/3?nav=tocList&quot;&gt;Journal of New Music Research&lt;/a&gt;. The article, “Musical Organics: A Heterarchical Approach to Digital Organology,” (it is published as Open Access - download &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/09298215.2017.1353636&quot;&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;) serves as a theoretical framework for a potential practical project that I, or someone else (a PhD project?) would develop in the future. However, in order to test the potential of the system I wrote a case-study of how a plugin to this system might work, and this was published in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ixi-audio.net/thor/Magnusson_NIME2017_MusicalOrganics.pdf&quot;&gt;Proceedings of NIME&lt;/a&gt;, a conference held in Copenhagen, in May 2017. The feedback from NIME was invaluable: I discussed the project with organologists, online instrument database curators, instrument designers, composers, and performers. The concept resonates with people, but we agree that the technical hurdles are big, challenging, and interesting. That was the feedback I also got from participants in the DPASSH conference, an altogether different gathering of people, in this case information scientists, digital humanities people, librarians, computer scientists and engineers. It was a real privilege to be able to present the work for them and learn from their feedback. Finally, at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sparc.london/touch-symposium&quot;&gt;Touching Sound symposium&lt;/a&gt;, organised by the SPARC people at City University in London, I had the opportunity to present work on the digital organology as a “provocation,” which is a great format when testing new ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel I have gathered enough insight to take this project further. However, it is time consuming and my busy schedule does not allow for such core development. I would welcome collaborations, PhD proposals, or suggestions for grant proposals, as I am confident that this project will become reality in the near future. The next step is to discuss it with my colleagues in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sussex.ac.uk/shl/&quot;&gt;Sussex Humanities Lab&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/musicalorganics</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/musicalorganics</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonic Writing Residencies in the US</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent a few weeks during April and May in the US, visiting my research partners there: &lt;a href=&quot;http://cnmat.berkeley.edu&quot;&gt;CNMAT&lt;/a&gt; at UC Berkeley and &lt;a href=&quot;http://cmc.music.columbia.edu&quot;&gt;CMC&lt;/a&gt; at Columbia University, New York. The aim with the trip was to explore these key institutions, study their archives, interview people, and present my own research as well as organising a symposium and a workshop. This was an extremely fruitful trip: these two institutions have been key actors in the development of electronic and computer music for decades. CNMAT was founded in the late 1980s, and has been the location of some important research (I might mention the OSC protocol, the o-dot library, but also countless new music systems, pieces, and performances) under the direction of the interdisciplinary inventor and musician &lt;a href=&quot;http://music.berkeley.edu/who-was-david-wessel/&quot;&gt;David Wessel&lt;/a&gt;. The Computer Music Center at Columbia has a longer history, founded in 1958, as the Columbia-Princeton Electronic Music Center, by Vladimir Ussachevsky (1911-1990) and Otto Luening (1900-1996). Milton Babbitt began working at the center shortly after its inception (hence the early Princeton connection). Other composers affiliated with the center include Jon Appleton, Luciano Berio, Wendy Carlos, Charles Dodge, Halim El-Dabh, and Edgard Varèse. The RCA Mark II Synthesizer was a flagship technology of the centre right from its foundation and it is still standing, although not in a functional state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/markII.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The RCA Mark II synthesizer at CMC&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;The RCA Mark II synthesizer at CMC Columbia. This is actually bolted down in Brad Garton's office.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate in that shortly after I arrived to the Bay Area, the Recombinant Media Labs (RML), the Associates of Don Buchla, Gray Area, and Obscura Digital organised a two-day festival in celebration and rememberance of the synth pioneer Don Buchla. The festival was jam-packed with interesting performances, panel discussions, and an exhibition of Buchla technologies. See the programme &lt;a href=&quot;http://grayarea.org/event/don-buchla-memorial-concerts/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/day1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The RCA Mark II synthesizer at CMC&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Panel chaired by Geeta Dayal, with Ramon Sender, Morton Subotnick, David Rosenboom, and Alessandro Cortini.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/day2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The RCA Mark II synthesizer at CMC&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Panel chaired by Marc Kate, with Tom Oberheim, Dave Smith, Roger Lynn, Keith McMillen, and Jessica Rylan.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were some fantastic musical performances (and I’ll link to a clip of Suzanne Ciani’s performance here below), and I really enjoyed the two panels too. Buchla was an inspiring, life affirming fellow whose curiosity and engagement with new technologies (and perhaps more importantly, the mind) never ceased to take his explorations into new directions. I will probably post the two panel sessions soon on the Sonic Writing YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FXhaw_T2Y1Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sonic Writing book project is taking shape and it was great to meet up with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloomsbury.com/uk/academic/academic-subjects/music-and-sound-studies/&quot;&gt;Bloomsbury&lt;/a&gt; editor in New York. Considerable part of the trip was spent on meetings and interviews with some very interesting practitioners and researchers and I interviewed the following people (in this order): &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rogerlinndesign.com&quot;&gt;Roger Linn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://audiosynth.com&quot;&gt;James McCartney&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sonami.net&quot;&gt;Laeticia Sonami&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sevwave.com&quot;&gt;Suzanne Ciani&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pamelaz.com&quot;&gt;Pamela Z&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.edmundcampion.com&quot;&gt;Ed Campion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ramagottfried.com&quot;&gt;Rama Gottfried&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sites.music.columbia.edu/brad/&quot;&gt;Brad Garton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://kenbutler.squarespace.com&quot;&gt;Ken Butler&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://retiary.org/ls/&quot;&gt;Laurie Spiegel&lt;/a&gt;. An amazing group of people, all of whom have contributed so much to the way we think, compose and perform music with contemporary technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still digesting the interviews. They were all mind blowing in their own way, but if there is anything that appeared as a common thread in these discussions it might be the sensation that we are at the cusp of some drastic changes in music technology, in the way we as humans make, perform, and listen to music. Common observations regarded a certain fatigue with the digital media, caused largely by how strong and few the new media moguls have become and how their products affect social and political life, disillusioning anyone who was optimistic about the internet in its early days. This fatigue could be exemplified by a retro movement of modular synthesizers, acoustic instruments and hybrid versions of those, and DIY in instrument making. But parallel we observe developments in machine learning, where, in the past few years, some incredible developments have taken place. Machine learning will be used at all levels of musical creativity in the future, from computational creativity (composing whole pieces of music), to mapping and personalisation features in our musical instruments, to core sound synthesis, where parameter morphing will be achievable at a level unprecedented by physical modelling or concatenative synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We might see a parallel in how new music technologies in the past were the domain of a few privileged people who had access to the equipment at Bell Labs (such as Matthews and Spiegel), CMC (Ussayevsky and Babbit), or the San Francisco Tape Music Center (Buchla, Subotnick, Sender) - and later IRCAM, the Milano Studio, or STEIM. Equivalent technologies are all mostly available today for free in people’s laptops. However, what we consider today as the privileged spaces of new music are, for example, centres for spatialisation, like the wavefield synthesis systems at the Technical University in Berlin or IRCAM, or institutions with strong computer networks that enable research in machine learning applied on multicore GPU matrices. Access to such computer networks is limited to downtime at relatively few research institutions - and this is reminiscent to how computer artists in the 60s and 70s would work in the night in order to gain access to the mainfraime computers of that period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America was kind to me and I had a fantastic time. There was a large and depressing political shadow hovering over people, but living in the UK, I am accustomed to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I post a link to a recording that just came out when I was in New York. It’s a documentation of Tony Conrad’s collaboration with Laurie Spiegel and Rhys Chatham, performing in The Kitchen in 1972.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/315406792&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 May 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/ustrip</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/ustrip</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Sonic Writing workshop at Lydgalleriet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This three day workshop is offered to students at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uib.no/en/kmd&quot;&gt;UiB&lt;/a&gt; (The Faculty of Fine Art, Music and Design), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bas.org/en/About-BAS&quot;&gt;BAS&lt;/a&gt;,  (Bergen School of Architecture), and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.skrivekunst.no&quot;&gt;Creative writing&lt;/a&gt; (Skrivekunstakademiet i Hordaland). The workshop will explore our writing practices with a particular focus on sound. Ranging from abstract poetry, concrete poetry, textual musical notation, algorithmic notation, secondary musical notation, and graphic notation are all forms of writing that we will engage with during the workshop. We will make musical instruments, considering how their design is a process of writing. The workshop will be highly interdisciplinary - with participants from institutions of divergent practices - and we will apply knowledge from the diverse fields to the experimental and explorative process in thinking about sound, writing sound, about composing instruments, writing algorithms, speaking notes, drawing movement in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sonic Writing Logo&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this workshop, we aim to rethink the established notions we have of instrument, notation, score, poetry, sound, word, letter, gesture, movement. With a starting point in the idea of the metaphor as a process of signification, a prescribed mental movement, we will ask probing questions such as: What is the significance of sound? What’s the role of sound in poetry? What is the role of the visual sign? How do we write sound? Notate? Can we make tangible scores? Can instruments be written? How does a poem inherit music? How can tonality, tonal and timbral variations change the semantics of a recited poem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The workshop will start in the morning on a meeting and a discussion about the day’s topic. We will form small groups of people who collaborate over the day on a project that will be presented and perhaps performed in the afternoon. After the presentations we will discuss the projects and reflect upon our experience of the day. On Sunday the groups will present their final projects in a public event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Example project descriptions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;

&lt;li&gt; A rock, a can, a bottle, a string. What kind of instruments can be built out of the junk we find around us? How does the human body relate to the instrument?&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;li&gt; Which symbols do we create for describing sound? Notation for new instruments require new thinking, new design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Beckett's Ping. How does this story &quot;sound&quot;? How is it notated? How can it be recited? What sounds would be appropriate?&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;li&gt; A sheet of paper and a pen. How to notate on paper? Can the paper become an instrument? What's the sound of paper? What's the sound of the symbols written on the paper?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; How do variations in the recital of a poem change the semantics or the impact of the receiver?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; What is a tangible score? Can an instrument contain a musical score?&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Times&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morning sessions: 10:00-12:00  Wednesday, Thursday, Friday &lt;br /&gt;
Afternoon sessions: 15:00-17:00 Wednesday, Thursday, Friday &lt;br /&gt;
Final presentation session: 10:30 - Sunday (A Sonic Writing Brunch) &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more precise time-table with topics will be presented at the start of the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants don’t need to have any particular skills to join this workshop. We will make instruments out of rubbish, we will compose music with paper cuttings, we will find rhythms in poetry, and study sound in space. In order to achieve this, it is best to be in the possession of, in the spirit of Zen, an empty mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sunday Presentation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having worked on interdisciplinary investigations over the duration of the workshop, we will conclude the workshop with a public demonstration of projects, ideas, pieces, performances. These projects can be at all stages of development; indeed, we often find it more interesting to discuss work-in-progress than finished pieces. The presentation will be about ideas, about the clouds of dust generated by the workshop discussions, and not about concrete solutions. We welcome everyone to join us at this event of explorative investigations into sonic writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Workshop Leaders&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bergsveinn Birgisson&lt;/b&gt; is writer based in Bergen. He has published three books of poetry, four novels and a doctoral thesis focused on the cognitive and aesthetic aspects of Skaldic poetry from pre-Christian times. He writes in Icelandic and Norwegian. He has studied different traditional chanting techniques in Scandinavia. In his doctoral thesis he developed a analytic-method on poetry based on cognitive linguistics and psychology. Bergsveinn is currently working on a novel where feelings are in focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://no.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bergsveinn_Birgisson&quot;&gt;https://no.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bergsveinn_Birgisson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thor Magnusson&lt;/b&gt; is a lecturer in Music at the University of Sussex. His work focusses on the impact digital technologies have on musical creativity and practice, explored through software development, composition and performance. He is the co-founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ixi-audio.net&quot;&gt;ixi audio&lt;/a&gt;, and has developed audio software, systems of generative music composition, written computer music tutorials and created two musical live coding environments. As part of ixi, he has taught workshops in creative music coding and sound installations, and given presentations, performances and visiting lectures at diverse art institutions, conservatories, and universities internationally. Thor is currently working on a book called Sonic Writing, to be published by Bloomsbury in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org&quot;&gt;www.sonicwriting.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com/thormagnusson&quot;&gt;www.twitter.com/thormagnusson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/workshop</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/workshop</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Special Issue: Live Coding</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The third issue of the twentieth volume of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tandfonline.com/toc/rpdm20/12/2?nav=tocList&quot;&gt;International Journal of Performance Art and Digital Media&lt;/a&gt; was about live coding. Kate Sicchio and I edited this issue, and after a process that took about a year and a half, from early stages of planning to publication, the issue is out. We are very happy with the result: a publication of a cutting-edge technology of music writing by some fantastic authors, including Emma Cocker, Sally Jane Norman, Tim Sayer, Karen Burland and Alex McLean, Hester Reeve, Hannah Elizabeth Allan, Sam Aaron, Andrew R. Brown, Mauro Herrera et al., Chris Kiefer, Charlie Roberts, IOhannes m. zmölnig, with book reviews on Andy Clark’s &lt;i&gt;Surfin Uncertainty&lt;/i&gt; by Jelle Bruineberg and Tom Froese, and the edited volume &lt;i&gt;Digital Movement&lt;/i&gt; by Sarah Whatley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate and I would like to thank Professor Dave Collins for the great collaboration on this special issue. Dave is the founder of the journal and this issue was actually his last as the journal’s editor. We also congratulate Dr Maria Chatzichristodoulou on her new role as the editor in chief. IJPADM is an excellent platform to think about new technologies in the performing arts. The current call is on “Bodily Extensions and Performance (Avatars, Prosthesis, Cyborgs, Posthumans)” and can be found &lt;a href=&quot;http://explore.tandfonline.com/pages/cfp/rpdm-special-issue-call-for-papers&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. (the extended deadline is January 31st).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/chriskiefer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chris Kiefer&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Sussex colleague, Chris Kiefer, live coding. Chris has an article in the journal issue.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our editorial:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Writing with shaky hands&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;I am no doubt not the only one who writes in order to have no face. Do not ask who I am and do not ask me to remain the same: leave it to our bureaucrats and our police to see that our papers are in order. At least spare us their morality when we write.&lt;/cite&gt; (Foucault, 1972)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his introduction to the &lt;i&gt;Archaeology of Knowledge&lt;/i&gt;, Foucault objects to be defined as a writer of a solid identity in order to be able to move, change, and explore the unknown – labyrinths and underground passages – admitting that such writing is at times done with a ‘shaky hand’. This journal issue explores live coding, a performance practice that operates in a similar spirit of writing as an adventure and exploration, of deliberately rejecting definitions, of being heterogeneous in nature, and continually challenging its self-understanding through the practice of writing and rewriting – of defining and redefining – as a public performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although live coding attempts to escape definition, there are denoting statements that have traditionally described its activities, such as: writing software in real-time; changing a programme whilst it’s running; projecting the screen for the audience to participate in; writing as an improvisatory practice; composing live using textual notation; changing rules whilst following them; conversing with the computer in its own native language; thinking in public; creating and using bespoke systems tailored for on-the-fly performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live coding is an improvisatory performance method that has been applied in the diverse art forms, but historically it has been very prominent in music, perhaps due to the importance of the musical score, computer music, and the technological foundations of musical practice in general (as demonstrated by the history of musical instruments). Live coding can be used as a compositional technique in the studio without an audience, but in this issue we focus on live coding as a performance method where code is typically projected on the wall for the audience to engage with – observing the thought process and the composition as it happens, as well as partaking in interpretation (understanding how sounds, visuals, or movements derive from the notation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live coders programme, they write in public (Greek: &lt;i&gt;pro-graphein&lt;/i&gt;) – but they also &lt;i&gt;pre-gramme&lt;/i&gt;, that is, their algorithmic writing is conditioned by a system that has already been designed with careful considerations of expressivity, constraints, interface, and other concerns of human-machine interaction and performer-audience communication. Most live coders adopt or develop a system best matched to the ways they wish to communicate the writing of their work – manifest as music, visuals, or other art forms. It is a writing of a writing that will happen at a later stage, on a different stage! The initial multimodal system thus offers creative solutions to the specific problematics of the stage, the real-time actuality of the performance, and the openness of improvisatory practices. Whilst the live coding system is pregrammed, the subsequent performance act of programming processes digital media as fluid entities whose functionalities are subject to development and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this live coding special issue for the &lt;i&gt;International Journal of Performance Arts and Digital Media&lt;/i&gt; is to present live coding in its broader historical and aesthetic context; the issue offers a set of theoretical papers supplemented with focussed artistic statements exemplifying diverse live coding practices. Emma Cocker’s article &lt;i&gt;Performing Thinking in Action: The Meletē of Live Coding&lt;/i&gt; applies the Greek term &lt;i&gt;meletē&lt;/i&gt; to describe live coding as a meditative thought experiment; one that is publicly shared, a form of ‘thinking-in-action’. Live coding is here framed as a site for experimentation and negotiation between the spontaneous and the planned, the human and the machine. In &lt;i&gt;Setting Live Coding Performance in Wider Historical Contexts&lt;/i&gt;, Sally Jane Norman traces live coding practices of projecting liveness and poetic modelling back to historical examples involving the Sun King, Louis XIV, amongst others. A key theme in the article explores how live events are crafted as uniquely artistic material, overriding habitual frames of reference. This is a theme picked up by Tim Sayer, whose article &lt;i&gt;Cognitive Load and Live Coding: A Comparison with Improvisation using Traditional Instruments&lt;/i&gt;, explores the cognitive mechanisms applied in improvisation, specifically comparing the improvisational practices of live coding to those of instrumental music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several articles address audience perception in live coding, defining it as a practice where most commonly artists choose to ‘show their screens’. In &lt;i&gt;Understanding Live Coding Events&lt;/i&gt;, Burland and McLean provide a study that aims to ‘explore the motivations, experiences, and responses of live coding audiences and to examine their perceptions of the role and impact of the projected source code during live coding events’. This is an area that has not been investigated previously in any depth within the live coding literature, but live coders’ gesture of projecting code sets up a relationship between performer and audience that is rather unique in the performing arts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The connections of live coding with live art are also found within this special issue, with Hester Reeve reflecting on her work collaborating with live coders, and placing it into philosophical discourse. Reeve’s &lt;i&gt;Live Code, Live Art and the BwO Dissection&lt;/i&gt; draws out similarities in the practices of live coding and the practices of live art, and in &lt;i&gt;(en)Coding Performance: From Analogue to Digital&lt;/i&gt;, Hannah Allan looks to Fluxus performance work in order to find text-based pieces which echo work found in the live coding community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conceiving this issue, we decided to call for artist statements in order to establish a more concrete grounding to some of the philosophical arguments presented in the longer articles. These statements focus on issues arising directly from performance, including designing performance systems, playful interpretations of code, and pedagogical implications. The creation of a live coding environment that serves equally for virtuoso performance and as an educational tool is the subject of Sam Aaron’s article. In &lt;i&gt;Sonic Pi – Performance in Education, Technology and Art&lt;/i&gt;, Aaron discusses the development of Sonic Pi and argues that teaching is by nature a performance – any good educational tool should reflect that fact. Andrew Brown’s artist statement, &lt;i&gt;Performing with the Other: The Relationship of Musician and Machine in Live Coding&lt;/i&gt;, delves deeper into the performer-machine relationship with a phenomenological discussion of his own performance works. For Brown, the live coding system is not a mere instrument, but the live coder’s other – an entity that can respond to the live coder and exert its own character during performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other artist statements explore audience engagement through a variety of live coding practices. The Mexican live coding community’s contribution to this issue is a report authored by Mauro Herrera Machuca, Jaime Alonso Lobato Cardoso, José Alberto Torres Cerro and Fernando Javier Lomelí Bravo, reflecting on their performance system that merges natural language and code. For Herrera et al. have created framework that explores the understanding of code as literary commands aimed at audiences who may not have a computer programming background. Chris Kiefer discusses his web-based experiment &lt;i&gt;ApProgXimate Audio&lt;/i&gt; as a way to invite participants to live coding practices through a system that applies simple commands to explore complex sound synthesis. Kiefer wants his work to be accessible to lay audience and novice live coders and he therefore applies the Web Audio API, an audio synthesis framework that runs in most modern browsers. Charlie Roberts’s &lt;i&gt;Gibber&lt;/i&gt; system is also written in the Web Audio API, and it enables live updating of code, where the text can respond to sound through the events it defines as notation. Roberts also discusses public engagement through the use of visual elements to reinforce audience attention throughout performances. Finally, IOhannes m zmölnig critically explores the issue of how text is understood by the audience on screen, discussing his multi-layered representation of code, simultaneously hiding and revealing, thus lending itself to multiple readings by audience members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reflecting on the articles of this live coding special issue of IJPADM, the culture of live coding emerges as one that is not overly concerned with the act of programming itself, but rather with the techno-social aspects of its performative systems, representations of composition, rule-based improvisation, and performance activity. These critical discussions are not on technology per se, but rather on how audiences, artists and learners read, engage, and create with code that is developing in real-time, on the fly, or live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live coding is maturing as an artistic performance method. This history has been documented from its beginnings as a focussed practice in the early 2000s (see Collins et al. 2003), to Magnusson’s (2014) discussion of products, practices, experiments, and performances drawing on 10 years of hindsight. The latter article speculates on live coding as a method that will become increasingly ubiquitous in diverse art forms, to the degree that we may not need the term live coding in the future. As this special issue demonstrates, the activities currently denoted as live coding are methods that can be seen to have historical precedents in the arts, but they also relate to problems studied in computer science, often under the term live programming (Tanimoto 2013). Presenting live coding in these broad terms, relating it to past practices and related research fields, makes it increasingly hard to incisively define. It appears that the popularity of live coding can be explained by its appeal to people growing up with interactive media who reject being subjectified as passive consumers of technology. Live coding represents a mindset of sorts that conceives of technology as fluid phenomena, offering an openness to change and exploration, such as live redesign of instruments, live rewriting of scores, or indeed of writing with ‘shaky hands’ in order to have no face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;References&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collins, Nick, Alex McLean, Julian Rohrhuber, and Adrian Ward. 2003. “Live Coding in Laptop Performance.” Organised Sound 8 (3): 321–330.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foucault, Michel. 1972. The Archaeology of Knowledge and the Discourse of Language. New York: Pantheon Books, 17&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magnusson, Thor. 2014. “Herding Cats: Observing Live Coding in the Wild.” Computer Music Journal 38 (1): 8–16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanimoto, Steve. 2013. “A Perspective on the Evolution of Live Programming.” LIVE 2013 symposium proceedings, ICSE conference, San Francisco.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2017 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/livecoding</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/livecoding</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Annotating New Notations at Ircam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ismm.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;ISMM team&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;IRCAM&lt;/a&gt;, we organised a symposium on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/ircam.html&quot;&gt;New Notations&lt;/a&gt; in September 2016. The focus was on new notational practices in the context of recent developments in new instruments and digital media. We programmed a day that would enable critical study of the changes in notational strategies brought forward with new music technologies, where graphics, animation, and algorithmic techniques offer extended compositional possibilities. Twelve international practitioners and researchers were invited to address key topics of prescriptive writing of sound for musical performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;notation and tradition - how does a notational language evolve?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;new instruments - how does the role of notation change with new technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the symbol and the material - do new ergonomic and timbral affordances require new symbolism?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;the evolving instrument - how do we compose for evolving technologies?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;notation in screen-based and computational media - what are the qualities of dynamic scores?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;graphic notation, live notation, animated notation - how does concept of &quot;liveness&quot; change?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;education and learning - how do we learn new notations for new digital instruments?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;audience understanding - how do we communicate what a notation system does?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;how does a notation system evolve, and how do we understand that evolution?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;what does a musical notation system mediate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ryan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryan Ross Smith&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;An extract from Ryan Ross Smith's animated notation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symposium ran over two days. We started the first day with thirteen short presentations by key practitioners in the field. The aim was to establish a context for further discussions in the afternoon and during workshops the following day. Jonathan Impett’s talk on “Notation as technology”, was a brilliant introduction to the symposium, framing notation as a technology in evolution, discussing hegemonic notation and how notation is becoming porous with other technologies. Sally Jane Norman’s talk “New Notations and Embodied Experience”, raised issues of how we notate human gestures, tracing technologies of recording and the notation of human action. She brought up the importance of being able to read machine readings of human gestures, a question of interfacing and representation. Enrique Tomás’ “Towards Non-linguistic Writing for Music: A Performative Approach” stated that we have become prisoners of representation and that we should “activate the body first, and let the mind observe the result”, pointing to performative materialities in his work on tangible scores. Ryan Ross Smith’s talk “The Trappings of Choice: Mediating the Democratization of Participation through Control” presented a history of animated notation, culminating in his own excellent work in that area. Franziska Schroeder’s talk “The absence of notation - exploring a haptic aurality” explored the relationship between notation and improvisation, and how non-notated musical practice can establish stronger bonds between the musicians on stage. Frédéric Bevilacqua’s “Questions on notations for interactive systems” presentation demonstrated his work on modular music objects that are notational in their nature: they prescribe actions via their affordances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, after a performance session and lunch break, Pavlos Antoniadis presented his talk “Old notation, new interface: embodied navigation of complex piano notation with the GesTCom,” and explained that he sees notation as an interface. He demonstrated a model of embodied interaction with notation, called GesTCom, which enables the performer to learn musical scores via secondary gestural notation, or multilayered tablature. Dominique Fober’s talk “How technology affects the music score”  raised the question of how a musical language evolves and the role of technology in such developments. Dominique is the author of InScore, which he also demonstrated. Claudia Molitor gave a beautiful presentation, “A visual moment,” which combined a talk and a video piece, exploring notation as a mulilayered architectural space, where the score becomes both a ‘script’ to be interpreted as well as a conceptual space. Einar Torfi Einarsson discussed the connective and communicative role of the musical score in his talk “Notation’s struggle to the surface (or, towards concrete notation)”. Einar presented his ideas of found activities, resonating the 20th century found objects. The virtuoso cellist Frances-Marie Uitti’s talk “Signs and Symbols for a New Music” revealed an experienced performer’s perspective on why new instruments require new notational practices. My own (Thor Magnusson) contribution, “On Notating Algorithmic Machines,” focused on how live coding has become one of the key methods in real-time musical notation, where we can write code for equally for machines and humans. Finally, Thierry Coduys’s talk “Notating with IanniX - Score in space and time” gave a good overview of the impressive IanniX non-linear programmable graphical sequencer for digital art, a “6D representation of notation”, in his own words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before venturing out into the Parisian night for dinner and drinks, we concluded the day with performances and an open discussion about the pieces we heard, referencing the talks as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/paris.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parisian night&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;The mondaines who could not conceive of going to bed after the late dinner.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day began with a discussion about the talks of the previous day. The notion that notation is some kind of universal language or a transparent layer that communicates music beyond cultural contexts of bespoke practices was called into question. The fact that common Western notation has never been such a universal and prescriptive language, clearly renders new approaches to notation, including graphical notation, secondary notation, extended notation, verbal notation, etc. impossible to standardise or become a subject of a general acceptance. For that reason, we agreed that it is impossible to create any minimal standards or platforms of new symbolic notation, never mind guide books or manuals. Frances Marie-Uitti gave us an insight into her work in performing pieces with new notations, explaining some of the difficulties of interpretation involved when having to learn a new symbolic language at the same time as a new piece. There is typically a reason for why composers decide to adopt new notational practices – this type of notation conveys something that traditional notation cannot signify – and the learning process is therefore often longer and more difficult for the interpreter. We also discussed that although the score has a tendency to become an aesthetic object on its own – and it often is – ultimately it is really what the performer decides to do with it that matters: what music it engenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the discussion we had four workshops: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.animatednotation.com&quot;&gt;animated notation&lt;/a&gt; with Ryan Ross Smith; &lt;a href=&quot;http://imtr.ircam.fr/imtr/CataRT&quot;&gt;concatenative synthesis&lt;/a&gt; with Diemo Schwarz; &lt;a href=&quot;http://netem.org.uk&quot;&gt;Netem&lt;/a&gt; workshop with Alice Eldridge and Chris Kiefer; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iannix.org/en/&quot;&gt;IanniX&lt;/a&gt; workshop by Thierry Coduys and Guillaume Jacquemin; and finally a workshop in &lt;a href=&quot;http://cosima.ircam.fr&quot;&gt;CoSiMa&lt;/a&gt; with Norbert Schnell. The workshop leaders managed to brilliantly add meat onto the theoretical bones that we had been operating with in the previous sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentations and some of the performances were recorded on video. Many thanks to IRCAM for sharing them with us and to Éric de Gélis for the excellent editing. The videos can also be found on IRCAM’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://medias.ircam.fr/x22be39&quot;&gt;video channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thor Magnusson: Introduction to the Symposium&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N0lskydfpy4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jonathan Impett: Notation as technology&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OmYjkj650Kw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sally Jane Norman: New Notations and Embodied Experience&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-pOJPBfOpNw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Enrique Tomás: Towards Non-linguistic Writing for Music: A Performative Approach&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P2H9K8h1enQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ryan Ross Smith: The Trappings of Choice: Mediating the Democratization of Participation through Control&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QeBwSYbHcbQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Franziska Schroeder: The absence of notation - exploring a haptic aurality&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OhECwrxeuew&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Frederic Bevilacqua: Perspective on notating and annotating expressive movements for interactive systems&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/AL8FhijtbHY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pavlos Antoniadis : Old notation, new interface: embodied navigation of complex piano notation with the GesTCom&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IoImLFM0YnU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dominique Fober: How technology affects the music score&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/70A_aRpk-A0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Claudia Molitor: A visual moment&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GCxMnlmv1-E&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Einar Torfi Einarsson: Notation’s struggle to the surface (or, towards concrete notation)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QRK-mXjJWqg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Frances-Marie Uitti: Signs and Symbols for a New Music&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x2DhwAjKw4A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thor Magnusson: On Notating Algorithmic Machines&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XCvcbi4XRsg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Thierry Coduys: Notating with IanniX - Score in space and time&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/L5ar6Z0LNS8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;PERFORMANCES&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ryan Ross Smith: Study no. 56&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/shBaVhpIpJM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sally Jane Norman: Object of Notation&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mj6z094rj-Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pedro Rebelo: Cipher Series&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;456&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RAtq6P_-izQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/annotating</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/annotating</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Arts Research Symposium at AlgoMech</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.algomech.com&quot;&gt;Festival of Algorithmic and Mechanical Movement&lt;/a&gt; is taking place in Sheffield between 12th and 19th of November, 2016. With a wide reach into the diverse forms of art, the focus is on artistic engagement with the algorithmic and the mechanical (perhaps a humorous reference to software-hardware and mind-body dichotomies). A festival rather than a conference, the programme is packed with exciting and rather wonderful pieces of art, ranging from bio art through robotics to performance art of the algorithmic and the mechanical. The Sussex &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.emutelab.org&quot;&gt;Experimental Music Technologies Lab&lt;/a&gt; was invited to run the &lt;a href=&quot;http://miptl.org/site/performance/arts-research-at-the-festival-of-algorithmic-and-mechanical-movement/&quot;&gt;Arts Research Symposium&lt;/a&gt; as part of the festival. This was the festival’s “academic” face, a platform where researchers, artists and the general public came together for a dialogue about the role of algorithms and mechanics in the arts. I found the day very interesting, and below I will retrace the programme as I remember it, in order to remember more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/algomechcoffee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AlgoMech Coffee&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Morning coffee before starting the proceedings - (photo: Chris Kiefer)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with a presentations session, where people had 15 minutes to present their work. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.harlizius-klueck.de&quot;&gt;Ellen Harlizius-Klück&lt;/a&gt; began the session by presenting her work on weaving, mathematics and notation systems. A brilliant project that’s both technical, historical and philosophical, the hypothesis is that any historical period of human culture can be understood from the language related to its technical mode of existence. Metaphors derived from each historical period’s highest technology infiltrate its thought and language. For ancient Greeks that technology was weaving: metaphors from weaving would be used to explain the cosmos or the structure of the state. The project attempts to understand past thinking process via the technology of live coding weaving looms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://medialab-prado.es/person/jesus-jara-lopez&quot;&gt;Jesús Jara López&lt;/a&gt; presented work done at the MediaLab Prado in Madrid. The communal project &lt;a href=&quot;http://medialab-prado.es/article/autofabricantes&quot;&gt;Autofabricantes&lt;/a&gt; is a learning community for makers that focuses on building prosthetic objects. For example building robotic hands, or prosthetic hands, that might be used for humans, but designed by the person whose hand it will become. There is something beautiful about people designing their own bodily extensions, as a process of design, purpose and aesthetics. What came up in the discussion was that a person who has never had a left hand might not necessarily want a hand with five fingers on it, as the medical profession would automatically proscribe. They might want more fingers or less, or implements of any purpose and use: perhaps a modular system of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arandomprocessexperiment.blogspot.co.uk&quot;&gt;Susanne Palzer&lt;/a&gt;, a member of the Access Space team, discussed the Open Platform project that she has been working on for some years. Susanne is interested in questioning technology, bringing it to people by deconstructing it in live performances, exploring how creative processes can form during a live performance. A form of live coding, the project aims to reconfigure technologies, or as she says, to do “technology without technology.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://transmediale.de/content/alejandra-perez-nu-ez&quot;&gt;Alejandra Pérez Nuñez&lt;/a&gt; presented her &lt;i&gt;Yeast&lt;/i&gt; performance project. She focuses on the potential of yeast reactions as biological responses as part of more complex ecosystems. For Alejandra, her work is an onto-epistemological investigation where, through the sonification of the fermentation action of the yeast. Here the yeast has a form of knowing, a relationship with its owner, craving sugar or heat perhaps, but certainly set up as a node in a complex perceptual system. Barad’s intra-action was mentioned in this context, with the state external material properties becoming part of our sensory system via translation processes, such as sonification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eliseplans.net&quot;&gt;Elise Plans&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.me/davidplans&quot;&gt;David Plans&lt;/a&gt; presented their generative music systems in the form of mobile app, the audiovisual Ominator. Here the user’s voice affects the development of the music and the visuals in realtime, so the listener becomes an integral part of the piece, fusing the listening with performance and composition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.muresearchlab.com&quot;&gt;Giuseppe Torre&lt;/a&gt; raised a question regarding the creative machine, stating that no AI algorithm will ever make a computer a creative agent. For Giuseppe, a computer cannot even be given the status of an agent, it is merely a tool, and only humans can be creative. (computational creativity was a theme brilliantly explored by Luba Elliott in her performance intervention during the afternoon coffee break). Giuseppe presented his code art installation, &lt;i&gt;AI Prison&lt;/i&gt;, which asks if a system can independently self-organise and evolve its own memory paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alejandroalbornoz.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Alejandro Albornoz&lt;/a&gt; presented the impressive work of Chilean pioneer in computer music and algorithmic composition, Jose Vicente Asuar. A visionary and an inventor, Asuar created computers in the 1970s and released some works that are of historical interest, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SlTrmYWhvRk&quot;&gt;El Computator Virtuoso&lt;/a&gt; and Asi Hablo el Computador. See &lt;a href=&quot;http://pueblonuevo.cl&quot;&gt;Pueblonuevo&lt;/a&gt; for the music of Asuar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cargocollective.com/joanachicau&quot;&gt;Joana Chicau&lt;/a&gt; presented her choreographic work which focuses on arrangement of things in space (choreo - dance, but also space; graph - writing), and here, in particular, machine choreography. Joana impressively live coded in the browser, deconstructing the popular Google search page and turning into a choreographic space for exploring time, movement, and linguistic expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we had &lt;a href=&quot;https://rosasencis.org/&quot;&gt;Rosamaria Kostic Cisneros&lt;/a&gt; presenting a beautifully organised project which introduces new technologies to the traditional practices in Romani/Gypsy communities. Participatory design, community engagement and bottom-up technology design were the key concepts in this interesting project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/godfried.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Godfried-Willem Raes&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Keynote speaker Godfried-Willem Raes explaining one of his musical robots - (photo: Chris Kiefer)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch we had a keynote by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.logosfoundation.org/godfried/cv-god-eng.html&quot;&gt;Godfried-Willem Raes&lt;/a&gt;. A composer, performer and robot engineer, Godfried is a pioneer and a catalytic force in European modernist and contemporary music. Godfried’s talk was personal, humorous and very informative. He first gave a short personal history of how he ended up creating musical robots, and discussing why robots are interesting in the historical development of music technologies.  It’s clear from Godfried’s work that he takes his role as musician to be one of performer and a communicator. For him music technologies are means to communicate with the audience, and thus require a seductive power: they are rhetorical devices. Having worked in the 1960s on electronic instruments, for Godfried it became interesting to work on robots since they are acoustic (as apposed to synthetic), they demonstrate the sonic action, and they exceed the physical capabilities of the human (such as being capable of playing 88 notes on the keyboard at the same time, or with microsecond intervals, each ‘finger’ with a different velocity value). A brilliant presentation, which we’ll have online hopefully soon, but in the meantime, here is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DEjPlGIFuOE&quot;&gt;Ted Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had two specialist panels during the day: the first one chaired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://dy7dx.com/about-2/&quot;&gt;Derek Hales&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;b&gt;Speculative Hardware and Fictive Materialities&lt;/b&gt;, and the second one on &lt;b&gt;Maker Culture&lt;/b&gt;, chaired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.keepandshare.co.uk&quot;&gt;Amy Twigger Holroyd&lt;/a&gt;. The speculative panel was extremely rich in content and, fittingly, very speculative. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arts.ac.uk/csm/people/teaching-staff/culture-and-enterprise/jamie-brassett/&quot;&gt;Jamie Brassett&lt;/a&gt; discussed how the future enters the present in design, &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewhugill.com&quot;&gt;Andrew Hugill&lt;/a&gt; presented how pataphysics is the science of impossible solutions and thus a pertinent methodology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/maya-oppenheimer-29581326&quot;&gt;Maya Oppenheimer&lt;/a&gt; gave a presentation on her concept of dramaturgical devices, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hud.ac.uk/ourstaff/profile/index.php?staffid=756&quot;&gt;Spencer Roberts&lt;/a&gt; took us through a concept map of process philosophy and how it relates to future issues in design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@elluba&quot;&gt;Luba Elliot’s&lt;/a&gt; intervention, which involved audience engagement in performing a Turing-type AI test, where other members of the audience were the critics, we had the maker panel. This panel discussed how technological and cultural changes have created the conditions of an emphasised focus on making (something that the panel agreed was simply a condition of human existence). With &lt;a href=&quot;http://medialab-prado.es/person/jesus-jara-lopez&quot;&gt;Jesús Jara López&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.birdandbee.co.uk/about/&quot;&gt;Ryan Patrick Morley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tomtobia.com/#aboutme&quot;&gt;Tom Tobia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://tamarjanemillen.flavors.me&quot;&gt;Tamar Millen&lt;/a&gt; the discussion was engaging and interesting, framed by two quotes provided by Amy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Many practices of making can be considered a sort of ‘everyday resistance’, not just to a consumerist culture but also to a political system increasingly controlled by corporate interests and difficult for normal people to influence directly. (Amanda Williams and Joshua Tanenbaum)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then a little more cynical sounding Csikszentmihályi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;What is called ‘making’ in North America and Europe is, frankly, a luxurious pastime of wealthy people who rightly recognize that their lives are less full because they are alienated from material culture, almost all of which is products produced by corporate interests. Sadly, rather than address the problem, makers develop a hobby that solves the symptom for them, but if anything slightly strengthens the disease. (Chris Csikszentmihályi)&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/harmonograph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Harmony&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;The Harmony installation by Ryan Patrick Morley&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symposium ended in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://algomech.com/2016/#event12&quot;&gt;Millenium Gallery&lt;/a&gt; with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.birdandbee.co.uk/harmony/&quot;&gt;harmonograph installation&lt;/a&gt; by Ryan Patrick Morley, and performances by Tom Mudd on one button, Tim Shaw and John Bowers with modular hauntology, Joana Chicau with machinic choreography, Simon Blackmore clapping a sinewave, and Ryan Kirkbride live coding his FoxDot system. Or did it end there? Perhaps it ended in the Rutland Arms pub, or in &lt;a href=&quot;http://access-space.org&quot;&gt;Access Space&lt;/a&gt;, with smoke machines and pop-up sound systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Video recordings of the day can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL7zKSsiv2z-PM8MY0wvx14w1x-I5OMF_U&quot;&gt;YouTube Channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2016 13:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/algomech</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/algomech</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Remembering Musical Organics at STEIM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For a couple of beautiful spring days in May, a group of people came together for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sonicwriting.org/steim.html&quot;&gt;Musical Organics Symposium&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.steim.org&quot;&gt;STEIM&lt;/a&gt;, Amsterdam, to discuss the topic of new musical instruments. The aim was to question composition, performance, and instrument design in the context of our new materials: the processor-based meta-machines we use to build our expressive instruments. However, the symposium acknowledged that the “digital” didn’t appear from nowhere: our work continues research and development that has taken place for centuries across different musical cultures. For this reason, the practitioners and researchers invited to present at the symposium came from diverse interdisciplinary backgrounds. From a traditional violin maker to an electrical engineer, the range of expertise was, in itself, truly inspiring. Moreover, the participants also perfectly embodied the symposium emphasis on interdisciplinarity: that very violin maker conducts excellent research in digital sound modelling and the engineer is also a composer and instrument designer. Composers writing instruments, performers designing instruments live, improvisers notating in the form of code, software engineers performing on stage: the degree of fluidity between concepts and practices was immense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presenters at the symposium were: &lt;a href=&quot;http://tai-studio.org&quot;&gt;Till Bovermann&lt;/a&gt;, instrument designer and software engineer; &lt;a href=&quot;http://sarahnicolls.com&quot;&gt;Sarah Nicolls&lt;/a&gt;, composer, performer and instrument designer; &lt;a href=&quot;http://hansjohannsson.com&quot;&gt;Hans Jóhannsson&lt;/a&gt;, violin luthier and instrument engineer; &lt;a href=&quot;http://mlab.taik.fi/~korayt/&quot;&gt;Koray Tahiroğlu&lt;/a&gt;, musician and HCI researcher; &lt;a href=&quot;http://eavi.goldsmithsdigital.com/phd/adriana-sa1/&quot;&gt;Adriana Sá&lt;/a&gt;, interdisciplinary artist, performer and researcher; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eecs.qmul.ac.uk/~andrewm/&quot;&gt;Andrew McPherson&lt;/a&gt;, electrical engineer and composer; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.marijebaalman.eu&quot;&gt;Marije Baalman&lt;/a&gt;, live coder and installation artist; &lt;a href=&quot;https://petefurniss.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Pete Furniss&lt;/a&gt;, clarinettist, performer, software designer;  &lt;a href=&quot;https://jr.home.xs4all.nl&quot;&gt;Joel Ryan&lt;/a&gt;, composer, technologist, philosopher;  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.halldorulfarsson.info&quot;&gt;Halldór Úlfarsson&lt;/a&gt;, luthier, product designer and maker; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samduffy.co.uk&quot;&gt;Sam Duffy&lt;/a&gt;, saxophonist, HCI researcher, theorist; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://thormagnusson.github.io&quot;&gt;Thor Magnusson&lt;/a&gt;, a software designer, musician, writer. I’ve given people these “role descriptions” and I’m sure they would object to the categorisations (I already object to mine), but this is roughly how people appeared as actors with roles in the symposium. The symposium was open for registration and judging from the quality of the work of the 23 attendees who signed up for the day they could equally have been presenting themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/steimpeople.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Musical Organics Symposium&quot; /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;caption text-muted&quot;&gt;Pictures from the first day of the Musical Organics Symposium&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent the morning and afternoon of the first day listening to short presentations, where people contextualised their research with the symposium theme. In between and after the presentations, we had excellent performances by &lt;a href=&quot;http://stephaniepan.com&quot;&gt;Stephanie Pan&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://modularbrains.net&quot;&gt;Stelios Manousakis&lt;/a&gt;, Marije Baalman, Koray Tahiroğlu, Adriana Sá, Till Bovermann, and Pete Furniss. Somewhere in-between that we found a time to discuss the issues that had come up during the day, with very useful input from the audience. The discussion explored the concepts of composition, of performance on new instruments, how we communicate what we’re doing with new technologies, how to compose for new instruments, what happens to tradition and or legacy when technologies are in such flux. We also discussed how a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nime.org&quot;&gt;NIME&lt;/a&gt; (New Interfaces for Musical Expression) education might be designed - a topic we explored further in a workshop the following day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;b&gt;second day&lt;/b&gt; consisted of diverse discussions and workshops. We began by considering themes emerging from the presentations and the discussions we had already begun. How can new instruments be introduced, maintained, and sustained in terms of use? How can they be documented and archived (related to this, Andrew McPherson and others ran a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.duo.uio.no/bitstream/handle/10852/50604/nime2016_mcpherson_et_al.pdf?sequence=1&amp;amp;isAllowed=y&quot;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; related to this at this year’s NIME conference)? It is one thing to document the successes, but we discussed whether we also need an instrument cemetery, a NIME junkyard, where the mistakes go for a documented rot! Some of the best scientific papers are ones describing hypotheses that turn out to be false - would NIME benefit from such a repository? Might this allow designers better access to ideas that have been tried in the past, so that they can build on them rather than repeat them? Could it be that at times we learn more from mistakes than successes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a discussion that went far and wide, we had open workshops: we discussed Halldor Úlfarsson’s plans for his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.halldorulfarsson.info/halldorophone5/about_halldorophones/index.html&quot;&gt;Halldorophone&lt;/a&gt; instrument and Hans Jóhannsson demonstrated his &lt;a href=&quot;http://hansjohannsson.com/rapidweaver%20export/page22/exp.html&quot;&gt;21st Century violin&lt;/a&gt;, which incorporates interesting physical modeling techniques. Sarah Nicolls presented her wonderful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ta_U-H0cfPc&quot;&gt;Moments of Weightlessness&lt;/a&gt; performance on her Inside-out piano. We then split into two groups, one designing instruments with paper and another discussing what an education in the are of NIME or DMI (Digital Musical Instruments) might consist of. The idea was to investigate if and how a musical culture, as the one we find around acoustic instruments, might appear around electronic and digital instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sonic Writing Research Fellow, Sam Duffy, took part in the workshop designing instruments with paper, facilitated by Till Bovermann, which explored aspects of human-computer interaction, product design, and psychology. She said: “We stripped instrument design back to basics, exploring the auditory possibilities of materials and form possible from a single sheet of paper. This was an opportunity to reflect on my personal desire to connect acoustic sound with digital opportunities. This was a meditative process in a beautiful surrounding and we were able to consider aspects of the environment, such as the effect of the wind on the sounds produced by the structures we created.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I participated in the education workshop. We had an interesting discussion on what a NIME curriculum would consist of. How might musicians best be educated to become skilled performers of new musical works? Firstly, it is unlikely that such an individual would be a performer only. We found it more likely that they would be composers, instrument makers, and performers, all at once. Considering the interdisciplinary role, such an education would be equally practical and theoretical - experimental and reflective. An important part would be to understand electricity and computer chips. Here, new types of notation will be learned: those of electrical schemata and computer code. In practice that would require some Arduino or Bela programming, as well as learning computational thinking with tools such as Pure Data, SuperCollider or Web Audio API. Sensors, motors, actuators; resistors, capacitors, transistors: these are the compositional materials at hand. Human-computer interaction, product design, and psychology are important elements of this type of study too. Understanding the human body, ergonomics, interface semiotics, and of course the most important elements, those hardest to measure quantitatively:  creative expression and the beauty and fun of a musical instrument. We listed these areas as a necessary technical underpinning for creating instruments, composing new musical pieces, and to be able to perform older pieces (or recreated older instruments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We agreed that we should not operate with dichotomies such as technical-musical, technical-compositional, or technical-theoretical: in this context the technical becomes compositional, and as live coding practice demonstrates, it is performative as well. Having fused such distinctions, we started thinking about the role of the body in acoustic instruments: the dexterity of the fingers, the human breath, the human limits for pulse (phrasing, rhythm) and gesture (starting, sustaining, stopping). How do these embodied parameters feature in electronic and hybrid instruments? Considering the body schemata and its limitations, the focus moves to mapping: how bodily gestures can be meaningfully translated to sound. And the idea of “meaningful” here also relates to how the audience can interpret what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A meaningful performance cannot exist without music of some interest and value. A student of NIME would have knowledge of music and instrument design from a global perspective, they would understand acoustics, culture, history and design. But most importantly, what needs to be taught and trained is performance practice. What the instrument is for? How it is played? How it works in ensemble with other instruments? How the performer connects to other performers? Or to the audience? How much theory is inscribed in the instrument, how much freedom does the performer have? Who takes these decisions? Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grounded NIME education will consider creativity at all levels of practice. How precisely to implement the above as an educational programme is a matter of institutional support, course goals, local research and musical cultures, and the personal style of the tutors. But this will be an education that stresses the role of context, community, and communication in musical practice. It will train approaches to invention and innovation. But just as in any musical education, what can’t be taught is the art of making good music - it can only form the conditions for that to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, writing this blog post, I came across this old &lt;a href=&quot;http://steim.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2012/01/STIEM-wire.pdf&quot;&gt;The Wire article on STEIM&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it might interest some. I thank the wonderful people at STEIM for welcoming the Sonic Writing project for a residency at their great institution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 11:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/rememberingsteim</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/rememberingsteim</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
